Guide to the Margot Gayle Papers 1959-2005 MS 241
New-York Historical Society
Margot Gayle papers
1959-2005 (bulk 1975-1990)
New-York Historical Society
MS 241
10 Linear feet (23 boxes)
Margot Gayle was an inveterate preservationist and journalist, active in many New York City endeavors to preserve historic areas and buildings. This collection contains her research materials, newspaper columns, photographs, and various publications related to her efforts as a preservationist.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Biographical Note
A longtime urban preservationist, civic activist, and author, Margot Gayle (née McCoy) was born in Kansas City, Missouri, on 14 May 1908. Moving frequently as a child as a result of her father's vicissitudes in the automobile business, Gayle attended the University of Michigan. Subsequently, she moved to Atlanta, began work as a social worker, and earned a master's degree in bacteriology from Emory University. Marrying accountant William T. Gayle, Margot contributed to the United States's World War II effort as a volunteer publicizing civil defense efforts. Next moving to New York City, Gayle inaugurated a variegated career that would include radio script writer, freelance magazine scribe, and public relations entrepreneur. Later she held public relations positions in city government; most important, she wrote a weekly architecture column in the Daily News for sixteen years. Producing two daughters, Carol Gayle and Gretchen Gayle Ellsworth, Gayle's marriage nonetheless ended in divorce in 1957, the same year she joined the Samuel J. Tilden Club, a Democratic Party reform group. The indefatigable Gayle also ran, albeit unsuccessfully, for City Council.
Notwithstanding her political activities, in 1957 Gayle spearheaded efforts to "save" the four stalled clocks adorning the Jefferson Market Courthouse, a brick and stone structure erected in the 1870s on 6th Avenue. Gayle's group succeeded by 1959 in convincing Mayor Robert Wagner to remove not only the clocks but perforce the building as well from the auctioneer's block. Moreover, Gayle's intrepid leadership netted a number of followers, including writers Jane Jacobs and Lewis Mumford and poet e.e. cummings. By 1961, the group succeeded in restarting the building's clocks; in 1967 the courthouse itself reopened as a public library. Her appetite whetted by the courthouse rescue, Gayle lobbied for a landmarks preservation law, which the city enacted in 1965. In 1966, impelled by the demolition of Pennsylvania Station, Gayle helped to establish the Victorian Society in America, a national non-profit organization committed to preserving the United States's nineteenth century heritage. Most important, she founded the Friends of Cast Iron Architecture in 1970, a group focused on the preservation of Victorian-era iron-fronted buildings. The group succeeded in opposing a proposed Lower Manhattan expressway in 1971 and in 1973 they won the establishment of the twenty-six block SoHo Cast Iron Historic District, which preserved buildings and artifacts and on the whole prevented SoHo from experiencing large-scale urban renewal. Gayle went on to fight to preserve cast-iron buildings around the country, as well as street clocks and lamp posts in New York City until her death in 2008 at the age of 100.
Scope and Content Note
The Margot Gayle Papers 1959-2005 (bulk 1975-1990) pivots around the civic efforts of Margot Gayle, particularly her efforts to preserve various New York City historical buildings, neighborhoods, and other civic monuments. Materials range from Gayle's completed columns (1975-1991) for the Daily News to subject files focusing on New York City buildings, streets, and persons, to correspondence to published materials to newspaper clippings to photographs to personal financial accounting materials. However, most materials relate to her later career as a preservationist; few deal with her early attempts at preservation, e.g. with the Jefferson Market Courthouse, with her forays into New York City political life, or with her personal or professional endeavors prior to the 1970s. She saved numerous publications, meanwhile, that range from published books to neighborhood pamphlets to maps dating from the 1880s to the 2000s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged within the following four series:
Missing Title
Series I. Daily News Columns and Related Materials
Series II. Subject Materials
Series III. Published Material
Series IV. Visual Material
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
For more information on conservation activities in Manhattan, please see the Shirley Hayes Papers.
Community foundations; Historic preservation.; Urban renewal -- Citizen participation; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration.; Historic districts -- Conservation and restoration; Historic sites -- Conservation and restoration; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); SoHo (New York, N.Y.); TriBeCa (New York, N.Y.); Upper East Side (New York, N.Y.); Cast-iron fronts (Architecture); Cast iron -- Societies, etc.; City planning; Daily news (New York, N.Y.: 1920); Friends of Cast Iron Architecture; Victorian Society in America
- Series I: Daily News Columns and Related Materials
  Scope and Contents note
  This series focuses on Gayle's role as a journalist. Almost every folder uses the title Gayle gave to it. Similarly, each folder contains Gayle's research notes for a Daily News column, as well as relevant clippings and photographs and a final copy of the finished article. It is arranged chronologically by date of publication of completed article.
  - Appellate Division Courthouse, 1975 March 23 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ruppert Brewery, 1975 April 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oriental Pavilion - Prospect Park, 1975 May 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Times Square - Olympic Theater, 1975 May 18 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sugar Refinery - Williamsburg, Brooklyn, 1975 May 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Williamsburg Bridge Plaza - Brooklyn, 1975 June 1 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Arch in Grand Army Plaza, 1975 June 22 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Flatbush and Fulton intersection, 1975 June 29 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brooklyn Eagle Building, 1975 July 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Union Square Savings Bank, 1975 July 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - J. Kurtz & Sons Building, 1975 July 20 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Willoughby Street - Brooklyn, 1975 July 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - St. Nicholas Avenue, 1975 August 3 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Flatbush Ave. Extension, 1975 August 10 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Old Pennsylvania Station, 1975 August 17 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Metropolitan Ave. & Union Ave. - Brooklyn, 1975 August 24 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flatbush Ave. "Junction", 1975 August 31 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Broadway (north from 136th St.), 1975 September 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Old Madison Square Garden, 1975 September 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ziegfeld Theatre, 1975 September 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - South Street near Brooklyn Bridge, 1975 September 28 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Steeplechase Park at Coney Island, 1975 October 5 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Broadway - the Bronx, 1975 October 19 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn Bridge Approach, 1975 November 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - Skyline from Staten Island Ferry, 1975 November 23 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
  - New York's Changing Scene - Anniversary Special, 1975 November 30 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fulton Ferry, 1975 December 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
  - Armory/Tompkins Market, 1976 January 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
  - Broadway (north from Franklin St.), 1976 February 8 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
  - Ferry Piers to South Brooklyn, 1976 February 20 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sixth Ave. between 14th St. and 23rd St., 1976 February 29 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bowery Savings Bank, 1976 March 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fifth Ave. (south across 59th St.), 1976 March 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
  - Williamsburg Bridge, 1976 April 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
  - Court St. - Brooklyn, 1976 May 2 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fifth Ave. - northwest corner of 51st St., 1976 May 16 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
  - Union Square, 1976 May 23 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
  - Crocheron House, 1976 June 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
  - Ocean Ave. - Brooklyn, 1976 August 8 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hospital for Special Surgery, 1976 August 15 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sightseeing Bus and Flatiron Building, 1976 August 22 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Entrance to Brooklyn Bridge (Manhattan side), 1976 August 29 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - McCreery's Department Store, 1976 September 5 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Riverside Dr. (north across 96th St.), 1976 September 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dodge Mansion, 1976 September 19 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Breezy Hill House, 1976 October 3 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bridge of Sighs, 1976 October 10 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - South St. & Brooklyn Ferry, 1976 October 24 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ernest Mitchell House, 1976 November 7 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fifth Ave. (southwest corner at 34th St.), 1976 December 5 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Holland House, 1976 December 5 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  - George Washington Bridge, 1976 December 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pier A at Battery Park, 1976 December 24 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Subway Kiosks at 23rd St., 1977 February 6 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - Shoveling Snow - Broadway and 23rd St, 1977 February 27 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fulton St. & Arbuckle Building, 1977 May 8 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - West 43rd St. Firehouse, 1977 May 22 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Appellate Division Courthouse, 1977 July 24 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Washington Bridge at 181st St., 1977 August 14 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Queens Public School 15, 1977 August 28 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Jackson Heights Public School 12, 1977 October 2 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Theodore Roosevelt House, 1977 October 22 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - West 23rd St. Ferry, 1977 November 20 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Queens Public School 55, 1977 December 4 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Union Square, 1977 December 18 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Columbus Circle, 1978 January 8 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Methodist Hospital - Park Slope, Brooklyn, 1978 January 15 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - East River Docks - Wall St., 1978 February 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
  - St. Agnes Chapel, 1978 February 19 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ninth Ave. at 40th St. El, 1978 March 19 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ruppert Brewery, 1978 April 2 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  - Samuel Morse House, 1978 April 9 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
  - Old Public School 36 - Brooklyn, 1978 April 23 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
  - Empire Blvd. & Flatbush Ave., 1978 May 7 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hindenburg Dirigible over Manhattan, 1978 July 2 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 37)
  - Recreation Pier - 3rd St., 1978 July 16 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 38)
  - Fifth Ave. & 42nd St., 1978 August 6 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Old Public School 90 - Brooklyn, 1978 November 12 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jefferson Market Courthouse, 1978 November 26 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Barge Office, 1978 December 24 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sixth Ave. El Station at 42nd St., 1978 December 31 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gane's Theater/Gimbel's Store, 1979 January 14 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - Public School 3, 1979 January 21 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Old Hall of Records, 1979 February 25 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Public School 131 - Brooklyn, 1979 March 4 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - City Hall, 1979 March 11 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Downtown Delmonico's Restaurant, 1979 March 25 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Row Houses - 84th St. and 85th St., 1979 April 1 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1892 Ice Cream Parlor, 1979 April 8 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gilsey Building/U.S. Steel Building, 1979 April 15 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Manhattan's southern tip from air, 1979 April 22 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - Nassau St., 1979 April 29 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
  - Uptown Delmonico's Restaurant, 1979 May 20 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - Third Ave. & 29th St. El, 1979 June 3 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
  - Broadway at 81st St., 1979 June 10 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
  - Third Ave. El Tracks, 1979 June 17 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
  - Radio City Music Hall, 1979 July 15 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
  - RCA Building, 1979 August 5 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
  - New York Life Insurance Co., 1979 August 12 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
  - Mount Loretto, 1979 August 19 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
  - Pete's Tavern, 1979 September 2 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
  - Manhattan Market, 1979 September 9 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
  - Garment District - 7th Ave., 1979 September 16 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
  - Riverside Church, 1979 September 23 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
  - East 63rd St. toward 3rd Ave. El, 1979 October 14 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
  - Grand Central Depot, 1979 October 21 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Cooper Union & El Tracks, 1979 October 28 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - 125th St. & 7th Ave., 1979 November 4 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Edison Headquarters, 1979 November 11 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - Empire State Building, 1979 November 18 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
  - Pavilion Hotel - Staten Island, 1979 December 2 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - King's County Courthouse, 1979 December 9 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - New York Eye and Ear Infirmary, 1979 December 23 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - Under the El - Jamaica, Queens, 1980 January 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mayor Harper House, 1980 January 20 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Temporary Washington Arch, 1980 February 3 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - Alice Austen House, 1980 February 17 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - Spingler Hotel, 1980 February 24 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Circus Parade - Jamaica El, 1980 March 9 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hinck's Ice Cream Parlor, 1980 March 16 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - Fulton St., 1980 March 30 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
  - St.-John's-in-the-Village, 1980 April 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - Egler's Bakery, 1980 April 13 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
  - Academy of Music, 1980 April 20 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - Lincoln Statue - Union Square, 1980 April 27 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
  - Boston Rd & 167th St. - the Bronx, 1980 May 4 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Third Ave. El, 1980 May 11 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
  - Broadway Looking North from Canal St., 1980 May 18 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
  - Wanamaker's Department Store, 1980 May 25 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
  - Central Park - Newel Post, 1980 June 1 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
  - Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 1980 June 29 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
  - Grand Central Station, 1980 July 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
  - East 39th St. - Murray Hill, 1980 July 20 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
  - Federal Hall, 1980 August 17 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
  - Brooklyn Museum, 1980 August 24 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
  - Union League Club, 1980 September 21 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mineral Springs Pavilion, 1980 September 28 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
  - Lord & Taylor Department Store, 1980 October 5 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
  - Abigail Adams Smith House, 1980 October 12 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
  - Flatiron Building, 1980 November 30 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
  - Greenwood Cemetery, 1980 December 14 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
  - Carnegie Hall, 1980 December 21 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
  - Fulton Ferry House, 1980 December 28 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Park Avenue Iron Hotel, 1981 January 18 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Borough Hall looking North, 1981 February 15 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - St. Mark's Church - Bowery, 1981 March 1 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fat Tuesday's, 1981 March 8 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - St. John's Chapel, 1981 March 15 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Liberty Warehouse, 1981 April 5 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lalance & Grossjean Factory, 1981 April 12 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - Post Office - Brooklyn, 1981 April 19 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - St. Ann's Holy Trinity, 1981 April 26 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Sailors' Snug Harbor, 1981 May 3 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
  - 24 Fifth Ave. - Old Brevoort House, 1981 May 10 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - Young Men's Hebrew Association Building, 1981 May 17 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
  - Gracie Mansion, 1981 May 24 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
  - Richmondtown - Staten Island, 1981 May 31 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
  - Temple Emanu-El - 5th Ave. & 42nd St., 1981 June 7 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - Astor House, 1981 June 14 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
  - Fourth Ave. from 14th St., 1981 June 21 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
  - Lower 5th Ave., 1981 June 28 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
  - Eastern Hotel, 1981 July 12 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Dairy in Central Park, 1981 July 19 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
  - St. Joseph's Church, 1981 July 26 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
  - Bailer's Hotel, 1981 August 9 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 23)
  - Herald Square, 1981 August 16 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 24)
  - St. Bartholomew's Church, 1981 September 6 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 25)
  - Second Grand Central Depot, 1981 November 29 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
  - Peter Cooper Statue, 1981 December 13 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
  - Times Square, 1981 December 20 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
  - Hudson St., 1981 December 27 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29)
  - Waldorf-Astoria & Knickerbocker Bank, 1982 January 10 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Consolidated Gas Co., 1982 February 7 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ninth Ave. El, 1982 February 21 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - New York Society Library Society, 1982 March 14 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - St. Bartholomew's Church, 1982 March 28 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - 112 Prince St., 1982 June 13 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bennett House - Staten Island, 1982 July 18 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - Gori Marble Works, 1982 August 8 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
  - Broadway at Fulton St., 1982 August 15 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
  - Mott Haven Reformed Church, 1982 September 19 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
  - Grand Central Terminal, 1982 October 10 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
  - Northern Dispensary, 1982 November 14 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12)
  - Wynn Circle - Williamsburg, Brooklyn, 1982 November 21 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13)
  - Stuyvesant Square, 1982 December 19 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14)
  - Tiffany's Store, 1983 January 30 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15)
  - Old Fifth Ave. Hotel, 1983 February 6 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 16)
  - Rhinelander Gardens, 1983 March 6 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 17)
  - Washington Square Arch, 1983 March 27 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 18)
  - 48 & 50 King St., 1983 May 8 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 19)
  - Seventh Ward Bank, 1983 June 5 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 20)
  - Bryant Park, 1983 July 3 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 21)
  - Laing Stores, 1983 August 26 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 22)
  - National Academy of Design, 1983 September 25 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 23)
  - Fraunces Tavern, 1983 October 16 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 24)
  - Fifth Ave. T-Arm Street Lamps, 1984 January 22 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 25)
  - Wooden Fire Tower, 1984 July 15 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 26)
  - Belmont Hotel, 1984 November 11 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 27)
  - Astor Hotel, 1985 April 15 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 28)
  - Post Office in City Hall Park, 1985 May 5 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 29)
  - St. Luke's-in-the-Fields, 1985 June 16 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Croton Reservoir, 1985 July 28 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Audubon House, 1985 September 8 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Pulitzer World Building, 1985 September 22 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn Borough Hall, 1985 December 8 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
  - Madison Square Garden, 1986 January 19 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Museum, 1986 February 16 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
  - Farragut Statue, 1986 April 20 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
  - Broadway - East Side, 1986 May 11 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
  - Grace Church, 1986 June 11 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
  - James Monroe House, 1986 August 24 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rutgers Female Institute, 1986 September 7 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
  - Old Sugar House, 1986 September 14 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
  - North Reformed Dutch Church, 1986 September 21 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
  - Tatham & Brothers Building, 1986 September 28 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
  - International Design Center, 1986 October 5 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 16)
  - St. Denis Hotel and McCreery's, 1986 October 12 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 17)
  - Colwell Shot Tower, 1986 October 19 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 18)
  - Mission of the Immaculate Virgin, 1986 October 26 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 19)
  - Valentine Mott House, 1986 November 2 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 20)
  - Terra Cotta Works, 1986 November 9 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 21)
  - Refreshment Stand - 5th Ave. above 59th St., 1986 November 16 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 22)
  - Wolfe Building, 1986 November 23 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 23)
  - Bartholdi Hotel, 1986 November 30 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 24)
  - Lord & Taylor Department Store - Grand St. and Christie St., 1986 December 7 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 25)
  - "Spite House", 1986 December 14 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 26)
  - Harsen Homestead, 1986 December 21 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 27)
  - New York Stock Exchange, 1986 December 28 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 28)
  - Bensonhurst Train Station, 1987 January 4 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 29)
  - Crystal Palace - Bryant Park, 1987 January 11 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 30)
  - Columbia College, 1987 January 18 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
  - Prospect Park, 1987 January 25 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
  - Friends Seminary - Stuyvesant Park, 1987 February 1 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
  - King's County Penitentiary, 1987 February 8 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
  - Trinity Building, 1987 February 15 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
  - Fifth Ave. Triumphal Arch, 1987 February 22 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
  - Clinton Hall, 1987 March 1 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
  - Striker's Row, 1987 March 8 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
  - Schenck House, 1987 March 15 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
  - Temperance Fountain, 1987 March 22 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10)
  - Goat - 120th St. and Amsterdam Ave., 1987 March 29 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11)
  - Saks Fifth Ave. Store, 1987 April 5 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12)
  - Metropolitan Ave., 1987 April 12 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 13)
  - Lorelei Fountain, 1987 April 19 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 14)
  - Austin House - Staten Island, 1987 April 26 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15)
  - Rice Building, 1987 May 3 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 16)
  - Brooklyn Public Library, 1987 May 10 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 17)
  - Hansom and Taxi Cabs, 1987 May 17 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 18)
  - Bryant Park, 1987 May 24 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 19)
  - Electric Circus - 23 St. Mark's Place, 1987 May 31 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 20)
  - 33 Harrison St., 1987 June 7 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 21)
  - Prohibition Park, 1987 June 14 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 22)
  - Herald Square, 1987 June 21 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 23)